Zero points!
（青木大吾(あおきだいご)）０点
Zero!
（佐藤昭二(さとうしょうじ)）０点
Another zero!
（青木）また０点
Group A
Judging in Progress
Hall
Group A
Judging in Progress
Does Sendawara Natsume
only give out zeros?
Group A
Judging in Progress
（佐藤）千俵なつめは
０点しか出さねえのか？
Group A
Judging in Progress
The scoring equipment isn't broken, is it?
（青木）
機械が壊れてるわけじゃねえよな？
Group A
Judging in Progress
（黒木場(くろきば)リョウ）はあ～
That's Nakiri Alice's aide.
（佐藤）薙切アリスのお付きか
What dish will he present?
どんな料理作るんだ？
I heard he had quite the crowd lined up
at camp when we had to serve 200 people.
合宿の200食課題じゃ結構―
行列ができてたらしいぞ
（千俵(せんだわら)なつめ）ふ～ん
Kurokiba Ryou
Group A
That's the boy who was preparing lobsters.
伊勢エビをさばいてた子よね？
He was a completely different
person while he was cooking.
何だか調理中とは別人みたいだけど
Sendawara Natsume
Prelims Group A Chief Judge
CEO, Howbee Foods
（香田茂之進(こうだしげのしん)）うっ
（港坂巻人(みなとざかまきと)）うっ
Ah, the contrast between the fiery red of the lobster
and the vibrant yellow of the saffron rice is beautiful.
エビの燃えるような赤と―
鮮やかな黄色の
サフランライスとの対比が美しい
The lobster shell is immaculate,
足やひげも
傷つけることなく―
Kouda Shigenoshin
Gourmand
with no damage to the legs or antennae.
完璧に仕上げている
That is noteworthy.
確かに―
Minatozaka Makito
Executive Producer of
TV Show That's a Kitchen?
This delicate and elegant plating is unexpected,
豪快な調理からは
予想もつかない―
given his dynamic style of cooking.
何とも繊細優美な
盛り付けですね
Hmph. There are any number of
restaurants that serve lobster curry.
フンッ 伊勢エビカレーを
出す店なんて いくらでもあるし
Mere seafood curry is hardly worth the attention you're lavishing on it.
ただの魚介カレーじゃ
話にならないわ
A forest.
（なつめ）森…
I'm deep in a forest.
深い… 森
What is this?
（なつめ）一体 何なの？
What's behind this fragrance?
今の香りの正体は？
はむっ
Whoa, that's the first time today that Natsume-sama took a second bite!
なつめ様が初めて２口目を
How does it taste?
（女子生徒Ａ）味は？
What's it like?!
（男子生徒Ａ）どうなんだ？
The Competition of
the Blossoming Individuals
This is... Group A.
（佐々木由愛(ささきゆあ)）こちらＡブロック
Sasaki Yua
Group A Hostess
Candidate Kurokiba's dish
is currently being judged.
ただ今 黒木場選手の
審査中です
ふにゃ～
Sauce américaine forms the base of the curry,
ベースになっているのは
アメリケーヌソース
a French sauce made with the shells of crustaceans.
甲殻類の殻をこして作る
フランス料理のソースね
As for this deep forest fragrance,
そして この深い木々の香り
it must originate from...
この香りの正体は…
cognac!
コニャックだわ
That's high-quality brandy made in the area around Cognac, a town in western France.
フランス西部の街
コニャック周辺で作られる―
高品質のブランデーですなぁ
Of course!
そうか
As the brandy ages, it takes on the scent of the wood used for the barrels!
ブランデーは熟成している間に
たるの香りが移っていく
That's why this curry has rich woody notes of cedar and sandalwood.
だからこそ このカレーにも―
杉 白檀(びゃくだん)といった木々の
重厚な芳香が感じられたのか
That's exactly right.
そのとおりっす
Please note that, in order
to impart a richer fragrance,
ちなみにより深い香りを
加えるために―
I used the highest grade of cognac, Napoléon cognac.
最高クラスのナポレオン級
コニャックを使ってみました
To think that the fragrance of cognac could enhance curry to this extent!
コニャックの香りが
ここまでカレーを引き立てるとは…
This is a fabulous French lobster curry!
これは見事な
伊勢エビのフレンチカレーだ
He's the first one to get a positive reception from the judges!
初めて審査員を反応させたぞ
I always knew he was really good!
（男子生徒Ｂ）
やっぱ ものすげえ奴
だったんだな あいつ
It's been a while, Erina.
（薙切(なきり)アリス）お久しぶり えりな
Allow me to introduce him to you.
紹介するわね
Now I have an aide too.
私にも側近ができたの
This boy is your aide?
（薙切(なきり)えりな）アリスの側近？
Yes.
I found him in Scandinavia.
北欧で拾ってきたの
You sound like you adopted a stray dog.
犬でも拾ってきたみたいな…
Come on, Ryou-kun. Say hello.
（アリス）ほら リョウ君
ごあいさつ
Hey.
うっす
I see.
（えりな）なるほど
So this is why Alice picked him up.
アリスが見込んだだけの
実力はあるようね
（水戸(みと)郁魅(いくみ)）へえ～
Finally, a dish worth judging has shown itself.
やっと まともに
評価される品が出たな
But still...
（幸平創真(ゆきひらそうま)）でもよぉ
Is that really all there is to that dish?
あの料理って―
ほんとに今のでおしまいか？
W-Well, it wasn't horrible.
（なつめ）ま… まあ
悪くない品だったわ
I suppose this may be worth a few points.
これなら点数をつけてもいいかもね
Let me think—
では 採点を…
Ah.
Uh...
えっと…
あれ？
Oh, okay, here it was.
ここに あった
It's not over yet!
まだだ
The tasting isn't over.
試食を終えるのは まだ早いぜ
Do you really have to put that on every time?
それ いちいちやらなきゃ
ダメなわけ？
Hm, eye droppers?
ん？　スポイト？
どうやらこの中身も
コニャックのようだが？
It seems there's more cognac inside.
There's a part of the lobster
you haven't tasted yet.
まだ味わってない部分が
あんだろう？
It's what's in the lobster's head, the tomalley.
伊勢エビの頭ん中
エビみそだよ
Put a few drops of this inside the shell,
then slurp up the tomalley.
こいつを数滴 殻の中に
たらしてから みそをすする
That's the best way to eat it.
それが一番うまい食い方なんだよ
うっ… “すする”ですって？
Slurp?!
As if I could eat in such a crude manner!
そんな はしたないマネ
できるわけないでしょう？
At least crack the shell and
serve it on a plate or something.
せめて殻を割ってから
提供しなさいよ
What's with all the posturing?
な～に 澄ましてんだよ？
You—
（なつめ）なっ…
（黒木場）目ぇ 見りゃ分かんだよ
I can tell from the look in your eyes.
Why don't you show everyone your real face?
本性 見せてみな
Admit it, you want to suck it down right this second, don't you?
（なつめ）はあ はあ…
（黒木場）本当は今すぐ―
むしゃぶりつきたいんだろ？
After you slurp the cognac and tomalley,
（黒木場）このコニャックと
エビみそをすすってから―
stuff your mouth with roux and saffron rice again.
もう一度ルーとサフランライスを
頬張ってみろ
It'll be so much better than
what you had before.
（黒木場）さっきまでとは―
比べものにならねえ
うまさだからよ
So much better than before?!
（なつめ）さっきより…
もっと？
はむっ はむっ…
The delicious flavor of seafood bursts in your mouth
and mingles with the deep fragrance of the forest!
（なつめ）
ほとばしる海鮮の美味と―
奥深い木々の芳香が
混ざり合う！
意識が…
I feel...
faint...
飛ぶ～っ！
Candidate Kurokiba, 93 points!
（由愛）黒木場選手―
93点！
Wow!
Group A    RANKING
Group A
1st
Kurokiba Ryou
2nd
Negami Haruka
3rd
Unzan Atsuya
4th
Kariyazaki Moeko
5th
Bakuzan Yoshitake
（観客たち）お～っ！
（男子生徒Ｃ）すっげえ～！
He's so far ahead!
（男子生徒Ｄ）ダントツ！
I can't believe this!
（女子生徒Ｂ）信じられない
93 points?!
（男子生徒Ｅ）93点？
I thought Hayama Akira would be
the one to win Group A by a landslide.
（男子生徒Ｆ）
Ａブロックは葉山アキラの
一人勝ちだと思ってたのに
Talk about a dark horse candidate!
（男子生徒Ｇ）
とんでもないダークホースが
出てきやがった
I've been continually thrown
into culinary fields of battle...
（黒木場）物心ついたとき
俺はもう放り込まれてた
for as long as I can remember.
食の戦場にな
Compared to that, this is a walk in the park!
ヌルいぜ
（黒木場）ここは…
What an amazing score!
（女子生徒Ｃ）すごい高得点
Is there anyone who can score higher than him?!
（男子生徒Ｈ）あんなの
超えられるやつなんているのかよ？
Well, that's that.
終わった～
93 points, huh.
93点か
Group A    RANKING
Group A
1st
Kurokiba Ryou
2nd
Negami Haruka
3rd
Unzan Atsuya
4th
Kariyazaki Moeko
5th
Bakuzan Yoshitake
（榊涼(さかきりょうこ)子）うっ…
アハッ… いやはや驚いたね
I must say, that was quite a surprise.
最高でも70や80点台止まりという
年もありますからな
There have been years where the scores topped out in the 70's or 80's.
Th-That was a total ambush.
（なつめ）
さ… さっきは不意打ちだったわ
I never expected anything that impressive.
まさかあんなすごい品が
出てくるなんて
I need to calm down.
いったん落ち着いて
Very well, th-the next candidate, please!
ああ… つ… つ… 次の方
お… お願いしますぅ！
Oh!
（香田）お～っ！
（港坂）こ… これは…
Wh-What's this?
Please enjoy. My curry dish is...
（郁魅）さあ 召し上がれ
あたしのカレー料理は―
Dongpo pork curry!
“トンポーロウ･カレー丼”だ
Dongpo pork is a dish where pork belly is braised with soy sauce.
トンポーロウといえば―
豚バラ肉をしょうゆなどで煮含め
仕上げる料理だが―
But never mind that. Look at
how beautiful this meat is!
見てください　この肉の美しさ
It's glistening!
照り輝いている！
Because the alternating layers of meat
and fat appear to be stacked threefold,
赤身と脂身が
交互に三層を成すことから―
“三枚肉”とも
呼ばれる部位ですなぁ
pork belly is sometimes called "three-layer meat."
Even the slightest touch of the bowl sets the meat quivering.
皿に軽く触れただけで
肉がプルプルと揺れる
Yet despite becoming so tender,
it has retained its shape!
ここまで柔らかくなっているのに
少しも煮崩れしてないとは―
It is proof that the cooking temperature was masterfully controlled.
相当な火入れの
バランス感覚が必要だ
This dish is sensuous in the extreme!
もはや官能の域
食べる前から舌が喜んでいるぅ～
Sensuous
Even before my first bite,
my tongue is aflutter with anticipation.
Sensuous
Looks like Mito-san's dish is
faring well with the judges too.
水戸さんの品も好印象のようね
Nice one, Nikumi.
やるじゃんか 肉魅(にくみ)
Awesome job, Nikumi!
（小西寛一(こにしかんいち)）すげえぞ 肉魅
That thick cut of meat must've
soaked up a lot of the tasty broth!
あの極厚の角切り肉
スープの旨味を
いやってほど吸い込んでるはずだ
I wonder what it'd be like
to take a huge bite out of that!
（汐見潤(しおみじゅん)）あんな肉
思いっきり頬張ったら… ジュルッ
どうなっちゃうんでしょう？
（なつめ）ま… 待ってよ
H-Hold on!
さっきの伊勢エビカレーの衝撃が
まだ収まってないのに…
I'm still recovering from the
impact of that lobster curry,
and now I'm supposed
to judge a dish like this?!
続けてこんな品を
畳みかけられたら…
What's the matter?
（郁魅）どうした？
Savor and enjoy this ultimate meat in all its glory.
たっぷり味わいなよ
極上の―
（郁魅）肉の快感を
（なつめ）ああっ…
Meat!
（なつめ）肉！
Meat
It's so tender!
とろっ… とろっ
はあ… かんだ途端に
肉汁が滝のようにあふれて…
The moment you bite into it,
Gush
the meat's juices gush out in a flood!
The gamy taste associated with skin-on pork belly has been erased by the spices.
（香田）
皮付き豚バラ肉特有の臭みは
スパイスの作用で消え去り―
The only flavors left are the
sweet fat and the rich curry.
舌に届くのは脂身の甘みと
カレーのコク
It's astounding!
何という うまさだ
After parboiling the pork belly,
I browned the meat,
下ゆでしてから表面を
香ばしく焼き上げたバラ肉を―
then braised it with soy sauce, oyster sauce, and Shaoxing wine.
しょうゆ オイスターソース
紹興酒(しょうこうしゅ)などで煮込んでいく
For spices, I used star anise, ginger, and Sichuan peppercorn.
香りづけのスパイスは
スターアニスにジンジャー
そして花椒(ホアジャオ)だ
But why is it that I can eat so much meat without feeling bloated?
（港坂）だが なぜだ？
これほどに
ボリューム感のある肉を―
なぜこうもスルスルと
食べられるのか？
そうか　このライスだ！
Of course! It's the rice!
ライスに少量の岩塩と―
The rice has a small amount of
rock salt and peppercorn oil mixed in!
香味油“藤椒油(タンジョウユ)”を
混ぜ合わせてある
The oil's numbing tingle and refreshing overtones cut the oiliness of the meat.
この藤椒油のしびれと
爽やかな香りが―
脂のギトギト感を和らげる
But it also makes you crave the sweet flavor of the fat, creating a virtuous cycle.
だがそうすると また
脂身の甘さが欲しくなるという循環
She's created a feedback loop
of delectability in this bowl!
この丼の中で
おいしさの連鎖を作っているんだ！
E-Excuse me! There are still
several dishes to be judged,
（かき込む音）
（由愛）あ… あの…
審査はまだ残ってますので
召し上がるのは ほどほどに…
so please be mindful of how much you eat.
No way...
（なつめ）…ないでしょ？
（由愛）はい？
What?
We know there are more dishes, but there's no way we can stop!
そんなこと言われたって
止められるわけないでしょぉ～！
Mito Ikumi...
（ローラン･シャペル）
水戸郁魅…
From the day she entered the academy, her intuition and knowledge of meat exceeded anyone else's.
入学当初から肉料理への理解と
センスは群を抜いていたが―
The problem was that she was prone to neglecting all of the other ingredients.
肉以外の食材への配慮が
薄い印象だった
But it's as clear as day from this dish that her cooking has evolved.
しかし…
彼女の料理
明らかに進化している
The fat and the roux are melting into a wonderful harmony in my mouth.
（香田）
脂身とカレールーのとろみが
口の中で混然一体に…
What bliss.
何という幸福感
JOY
This dish is so devastatingly good that it makes you believe this is the only way to cook pork belly.
（港坂）
皮付き豚バラ肉を味わうなら
これ以上の調理法はない
そう思わせるほどの破壊力
Devas-
tating
Without question, she is the Meat Master.
（香田）まさしくミートマスター
Meat Master
No, she is far better than that.
（港坂）いや 彼女はもっと上…
Oh, meat!
（なつめ）アイ･ニード･ユー
（香田･港坂）肉将軍(ミートジェネラル)！
（なつめ）ミート！
She is the Meat General!
Meat General
Meat!
（なつめ）ミート～！
Meat, oh!
Group A    RANKING
Group A
1st
Kurokiba Ryou
2nd
Mito Ikumi
3rd
Negami Haruka
4th
Unzan Atsuya
（由愛）水戸選手 86点！
Candidate Mito has scored 86 points!
（学生たち）お～っ！
（男子生徒Ｉ）出た 高得点！
What a high score!
（男子生徒Ｊ）暫定２位だ
That puts her solidly in second place!
Damn.
クソッ　90点に届かなかったか
I didn't make it into the 90's.
Nikumi, that was amazing!
（創真）肉魅～
（郁魅）あっ？
すげえじゃん
超うまそうだったぜ
It looked super tasty.
It's what I learned from you, Yukihira.
これは… 幸平から
教わったことだから
A don should be complete in one bowl, right?
“丼は一椀で”だろ？
You really do understand, huh?
（創真）よく分かってんじゃん
（郁魅）あっ…
Nikumi, good job!
肉魅～ いいぞ～！
Wow, I'm so relieved.
ああ よかった～
This is finally starting to feel like a competition!
やっと大会らしくなってきました
Let's keep this going!
この調子で参りましょう
Next up is Candidate Sakaki Ryouko.
続いては榊涼子選手
Please enjoy.
召し上がってください
It's everything I have to offer right now.
今の私の全てを
It looks pretty plain, doesn't it?
（男子生徒Ｋ）何か見た目は
よくある感じじゃねえか？
Compared to the previous dishes,
there isn't much visual impact.
（女子生徒Ｄ）
さっきのに比べたら
インパクト弱いような…
Hm, it look to be dal, also called pulse curry.
う～ん ダール
すなわち豆のカレーですか
It bears some resemblance to chana masala.
インドのチャナマサラの
ような品か…
Wait, I know this sticky substance!
ん？　この粘りは？
It's natto!
（港坂）納豆だ
（なつめ）はむっ
The viscosity and umami are coating my mouth.
（なつめ）粘りと旨味が
口の中に絡みついてくる
I didn't think natto could be this delicious.
納豆って
こんなにおいしいものだったの？
No, it's not just any natto.
いや ただの納豆じゃない
It can't be...
これは まさか…
It's natto made over a charcoal flame:
（涼子）それは炭火によって
作り上げた納豆
炭火熟成納豆です
charcoal-fermented natto.
Ventilate
regularly!!
I maintained a charcoal fire in an underground chamber to assure optimal temperature and humidity,
地下室で炭をたき続け―
Ventilate
regularly!!
最適な温度･湿度を保ち―
Ventilate
regularly!!
while soybeans were fermented with the natto spore for several days.
納豆菌を付着させた大豆を
数十時間かけて発酵させました
I made use of my time over
summer break to make it.
夏季休暇を利用して
仕込んでおいたものです
Slowly fermenting soybeans over a charcoal fire allows you to create a more complex flavor.
（観客Ａ）
炭火によりじっくり熟成…
より強いコクを生み出す製法だ
Fermentation
Since the natto mold isn't killed during this process,
（観客Ｂ）菌を殺すことがないので
アンモニア臭を抑える効果もある
Ammonia
the odor of ammonia is considerably less.
But that's not the only thing!
でも違う
それだけじゃないわ
何？　この舌に響く―
What is it?!
What is this umami that hits your palate like a deep bass note?
重低音のような
旨味の正体は？
My secret ingredient is soy sauce rice malt.
隠し味として
“しょうゆ麹(こうじ)”を加えています
Soy sauce rice malt!
しょうゆ麹か
First you mix soy sauce into rice malt.
米麹に しょうゆを混ぜ―
Then you let the mixture ferment for
several weeks at room temperature.
常温で数週間
発酵させて作る調味料
I get it.
そうか　調理中の―
The black substance I saw her using
あの黒い物は―
was the soy sauce rice malt,
しょうゆ麹
and the sticky substance was natto.
ねばついた物の正体は納豆か
Soy sauce rice malt has over ten times the glutamic acid of salted rice malt.
しょうゆ麹には旨味成分である
グルタミン酸が―
塩麹の10倍以上あります
That's how she could add more umami
without the strong curry flavor eclipsing it.
だからこそ
カレーの強さにも負けず―
うまさをプラスさせることが
できたのか
It's a great curry dish that takes full advantage of her mastery of fermentation.
（シャペル）
発酵の極意を存分に生かした
見事なカレー料理だ
The thick Japanese-style curry pairs well with the viscous natto.
（なつめ）ドロリとした
和風カレーが―
納豆の粘りと
よくなじんでいる
The generous pile of finely sliced
green onion is irresistible as well.
（香田）たっぷりとのせられた
小口切りのネギもたまりません
She has used her mastery over the
power of soybeans to perfect this dish.
（港坂）大豆の力を従え
完璧にまとめ上げている
I'd be proud to call her a sister-in-arms...
そんな彼女を僕は
“姉さん”と―
or rather, Mistress!
いや “姐(あね)さん”と呼びたい！
（担ぎ手たち）
ソイ ソイ ソイ ソイ！
is English for soybeans
Flag bearers of the Fermentation Business
ソイ ソイ ソイ ソイ！
The Sakaki Clan
3rd
Negami Haruka
Unzan Atsuya
Candidate Sakaki has scored 86 points!
Group A    RANKING
Group A
1st
Kurokiba Ryou
2nd
Mito Ikumi
4th
（由愛）榊選手 86点！
Unzan Atsuya
2nd
Sakaki Ryouko
（観客たち）お～っ！
（由愛）水戸選手と同点です
That's the same score as Candidate Mito!
Good job, Sakaki!
いいぞぉ 榊ぃ～！
She's in second place!
２位に入ったぜ！
You make some really cool things, Sakaki.
（創真）榊も面白いもん作るよなぁ
（涼子）あっ？
Let me have some next time.
今度 食わせてくれよ
Sure. Of course!
ええ… もちろん
This place is getting fired up!
（男子生徒Ｌ）盛り上がってきたぞ
Who's next?
（女子生徒Ｅ）次は誰？
Oh...
（女子生徒Ｆ）あっ…
（男子生徒Ｍ）何だ あいつか
It's him.
I bet most of the people here don't have any expectations of me.
（丸井善二(まるいぜんじ)）この会場にいる
ほとんどの人は―
僕には期待もしていないだろうね
Mr. Marui.
（男子生徒Ｎ）丸井氏！
（男子生徒Ｏ）丸井氏！
Mr. Marui!
（男子生徒Ｐ）丸井氏
Mr. Marui.
Good luck, Mr. Marui!
（榎本円(えのもとまどか)）頑張って 丸井氏
But just you watch. I'll stir things up.
でも僕は
風を起こしてみせるよ
Here, go ahead.
Enomoto Madoka
First-Year, High School
Good
luck!
Mr. Marui...
Keh!
Oh, um... uh...
（由愛）続いて丸井選手
披露してくださ… うっ…
Calm down!
Okay, I'm Enomoto Madoka!
Like Mr. Marui, I'm part of the Miyazato research lab.
Mr. Marui and I...
Me and Mr. Marui...
Next is Candidate Marui!
Please show us your di-
It's so white.
白い…
The roux and ingredients are all white!
ルーも具も全てが白です
（港坂）この麺 うどんだ
The noodles are udon.
They've been kneaded with cumin.
クミンが練り込んである
So this is your version of curry udon?
つまりこれは君ならではの
カレーうどんということだね？
Yes. It's white potage curry udon.
はい
“白のポタージュ
カレーうどん”です
Hm. It's quite beautiful.
うむ…
なかなかに美しい品ですなぁ
If Kurokiba-kun's dish was
a tumult of color,
黒木場君の品が色彩の
奔流だとすれば―
Tumult of Color
then this dish is
like a tranquil lake.
これは
静寂に満ちた泉のようだ
Tranquil Lake
Let us begin.
では…
Whatever, I doubt it'll get high marks.
（男子生徒Ｑ）
ま 大した点数は出ないだろう
The only thing I remember about Marui is that he was about to kick the bucket during camp.
（男子生徒Ｒ）
あの丸井って奴 合宿の時
ヘロヘロになっていた印象しか―
ないもんなぁ
（なつめ）うん うん はむっ
E-Excuse me...
あっ あのう…
どなたかそろそろコメントを…
Could one of you please comment on the dish?
P-Please don't ignore me!
（由愛）む… 無視しないでぇ～
What?!
（青木）エッヘヘ…
（男子生徒Ｓ）なに～！
They're all chowing down like there's no tomorrow!
（男子生徒Ｓ）
全員 夢中になって食ってる！
A plump poached egg, creamy mashed potatoes,
プルプルのポーチドエッグに
クリーミーなマッシュポテト
Poached Egg
Mashed Potatoes
and a generous amount of piping hot, melted cheese.
たっぷりとのせられた
とろとろの熱いチーズ
Melted Cheese
The roux is like a vichyssoise!
そしてルーは
ヴィシソワーズ風に仕上げてある
Vichysoisse Style
Vichyssoise...
ヴィシソワーズ
A dense soup made mainly from
potatoes and fresh cream.
主にジャガイモと
生クリームで作る冷製ポタージュ
It's a dish devised in 1917 by Louis Diat,
1917年に高級ホテル―
リッツカールトンの料理長―
the head chef of the luxury hotel Ritz-Carlton.
ルイ･ディアが
考案したメニューだな
Though it might appear to be thick and heavy, you can just keep on eating it.
ドロッとして一見 重そうなのに
スルスルと箸が進む
It's coriander that makes the udon so light, isn't it?
スルッと軽いうどんと―
コリアンダーパウダーの
おかげですね
Coriander is known for its mild overtones,
which is reminiscent of citrus, and its faint spiciness.
（なつめ）
柑橘系を思わせるまろやかさと―
かすかな辛味が特徴のスパイス
The synergy between it and the cumin in the noodles enhances the fragrance of both.
麺のクミンとも相性抜群で―
互いの香りを引き立てている
This is an unbelievably satisfying dish!
とてつもない満足感！
I have included dill, which is a
mainstay topping in vichyssoise.
ヴィシソワーズのトッピングに
欠かせないディルも使い―
By roasting the seeds of dill
and cumin together,
その種子とクミンシードを
併せ炒めることで―
I have created a very fragrant soup.
香り高いスープに仕上げています
He has taken the trendy dipping ramen concept and applied it to vichyssoise, a century-old dish!
（香田）近年のつけ麺感覚を―
Dipping Ramen
100年前のヴィシソワーズから
着想するとは―
How wonderful!
すばらしい一品だ
Mr. Marui!
（男子生徒Ｔ）丸井氏
Well done, Mr. Marui!
（男子生徒Ｕ）
さすがですぞ 丸井氏
Mr. Marui!
丸井氏
（宮里隆夫(みやざとたかお)）うんうん
Well done.
It's the perfect showcase for your talents, Marui Zenji.
最高のお披露目になったようだね
〝丸井善二〞という
才能の
Miyazato Takao
Professor, Miyazato Lab
At my research lab, we research and analyze historic texts on food.
美食に関する古典文献を
研究･分析する宮里ゼミ
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
The Physiology of Taste
The Pleasures of the Table by Brillat-Savarin
Le Guide Culinaire by Auguste Escoffier
Despite being only a first-year,
Marui-kun is the star of our lab.
丸井君はその中で１年生にして
エースを張る男なのだから
I don't have a keen sense for cooking.
（丸井）僕には
ずば抜けた料理センスはない
I tire faster than most people.
体力も人並み以下だ
That's all the more reason for me to study as hard as I do.
だからこそ知識をむさぼった
I am average, but I've set my sights
on reaching the geniuses.
凡才の僕が―
天才たちに食らいつくために
We at the lab have a name for him:
我々は彼をこう呼ぶ
the Professor of Taste!
“味の物知り博士”
The Professor of Taste
Candidate Marui has scored 88 points!
（由愛）丸井選手 88点！
（観客たち）お～っ！
He has second place all to himself!
（由愛）
単独２位に躍り出ました！
Marui!
（青木）丸井！
（佐藤）やったぜ！
Good job!
Professor!
教授 ほら 見てください 教授
Look, Professor!
Mr. Marui is in second place!
丸井氏が２位です ハハハハ…
フフ… そうだね
Indeed.
We've seen one high score after the other!
高得点の連続です
Will this trend continue?
この勢いは―
まだ止まらないのでしょうか？
Next is Candidate Ibusa—
次は伊武崎選手…
In terms of sheer power of fragrance...
香りの強烈さだけなら―
this dish may be number one!
今までで一番かも
Please enjoy my special smoked curry.
（伊武崎峻(いぶさきしゅん)）特製スモークカレー
ご賞味あれ
The toppings are smoked bacon,
（佐藤）
トッピングは薫製ベーコンに―
smoked potatoes,
薫製ポテト―
and a smoked egg?!
薫製卵？
You can't just smoke everything
and call it a day, Ibusaki!
何でもかんでも いぶせばいいって
もんじゃねえぞ 伊武崎
But it does look really tasty.
（佐藤･青木）でも うまそう～
D-Don't forget the theme is curry!
（なつめ）テ… テーマは
あくまでカレーよ
If you just smoke everything,
you'll overwhelm the spices.
やみくもに薫製して
スパイスの香りを殺すようでは…
はむっ
あっ ああ ああ～ん！
The dish was finished with coarsely ground cinnamon, cumin, cardamon, and cloves.
仕上げのスパイスはシナモン
クミン カルダモンと―
クローブの粗びき
Applewood wood chips were used
to cure these ingredients.
それにスモークチップには
リンゴが使われています
I see!
（港坂）なるほど
That's how he managed to enhance the spices rather than eclipsing them!
だからスパイスの風味を消さずに
むしろ引き立てているのか
Yes.
ええ　この粗びきスパイスを
最も生かすチップですなぁ
Applewood is the best choice for
working with these spices.
These coarsely-ground spices
were also added to the saumure,
粗びきスパイスは
いぶす前の塩漬けする工程で―
which is used to brine
ingredients prior to smoking.
ソミュール液にも
入れてあるんで―
Saumure Liquid
(Brine with Seasonings and Spices)
This infused the ingredients
with the curry's flavor.
具からも
カレーの風味が―
しっかり
感じられるはずです
The toppings are wonderful.
トッピングも抜かりない
This egg has been turned
into an umami bomb!
卵は 旨味がギューッと濃縮
The half-congealed yolk just
melts in your mouth.
半熟ゼリー状の黄身が
とろとろだ～
But wait.
（香田）いや しかし待てよ
How did he achieve cohesion between all the different ingredients?
各素材が バラバラにならず
見事に調和しているが―
How did he achieve such unity?
どうやってここまでの一体感を？
（香田）くわっ！
（なつめ･港坂）あっ？
I see! I understand it now!
そうか　分かったぞ
You used smoked salt in the spice mix!
ミックススパイスに加えた塩も
薫製にしてあるんだ
He smoked the salt?
（男子生徒Ｖ）塩まで薫製に？
But how much difference could that make?
（男子生徒Ｗ）
でもそれで味まで変わるのかよ？
I'll have you know I didn't use just any salt.
（伊武崎）ちなみに使ったのは
ただの塩じゃなく―
It's seaweed salt, made by burning seaweed with high sodium content, dissolving it in water,
Seaweed Salt
藻塩
塩分を多く含んだ海藻を
焼いて水に溶かし―
then boiling down the supernatant.
その上澄みを煮詰めて
作った塩です
Seaweed
Salt
So that's why the flavor is so rounded and mild.
（なつめ）
それで味に丸みとまろやかさが…
He achieved unity in this curry
by using smoked salt.
薫製塩の力で
カレーを調和させた
What an astounding boy.
（港坂）恐るべき少年だ
He has a complete grasp of what
flavors curing can bring to a dish.
薫製がもたらす味のイメージを
完璧に とらえている
Despite his youth, he has the skills to manipulate smoke at will.
年若くして
自由自在に煙を操るその技術
You are the...
ユー･アー･ザ…
Prince of Smoke!
燻煙の貴公子(プリンスオブスモーク)！
Prince
of Smoke
88 points!
（由愛）88点！
Candidate Ibusaki is now also in second place!
Group A    RANKING
Group A
1st
Kurokiba Ryou
2nd
Marui Zenji
Ibusaki Shun
4th
Mito Ikumi
Sakaki Ryouko
伊武崎選手 同率２位です
Whoa!
（観客たち）お～っ！
（創真）お～っ すげえぞ ２人とも
Good job, you two!
I've never seen the two of them like this.
こんな２人初めて見た
So only now do you reveal your true colors.
（伊武崎）
やっと人前で本性を見せたか
Look who's talking.
それを君が言うのかい？
Finally coming out from behind
that veil of smoke, are you?
君こそ秘密主義の男じゃないか
I guess.
まあな
（なつめ）ああ～っ
（男子生徒Ｖ）なつめ様がもう―
Natsume-sama looks like
she's reached her limits!
何か足腰 立たなくなってるぞ
Wow!
すっげえ！
There are three Polar Star
members in the top five!
トップ５に極星(きょくせい)勢が
３人も入ってるぜぇ！
Huh?
あっ ちょっと待てよ
Wait a second.
Only four get to advance to
the main tournament, right?
本戦へ勝ち上がるのは
４人だけだろ？
What happens if there are too
many with the same score?
同点がいるってことは…
If these standings still persist
after the judging is over,
（叡山(えいざん)枝津也(えつや)）もし最後まで順位が
このままの場合―
the five judges will vote to determine
who will proceed to the main tournament.
審査員５名による
決選投票となります
However...
（叡山）しかし…
There are still others.
まだ彼らが―
（シャペル）控えているか
（汐見）ああっ…
Next up is Candidate Hayama Akira.
（由愛）次は葉山アキラ選手
I made an extra portion just for you.
（葉山）カレー お前の分も
作っといたからよ
Oh? What a coincidence.
おお～っ 奇遇だな 俺もさ
So did I.
Let's have fun comparing.
食べ比べといこうぜ
Sure thing.
上等
Years Ago
Here you go.
（店主）はい 毎度あり
Huh?
あれ？
Um, isn't this...
あの… これって…
You got what you came for, so scram!
物を受け取ったら行った 行った
こっちは忙しいんだ
I'm busy!
What? But...
（汐見）えっ？
えっ… で… でも…
全体の３割ってとこか
I figure it's around 30 percent by weight.
You mixed in some poor quality spices, didn't you?
（葉山）香りの弱い粗悪品を
混ぜてあんだろ？
スラムのガキか
What would a slum rat like you know?
Just try and prove—
（店主）何を根拠にそんなことを…
（葉山）分かるんだよ
I can tell.
My nose is something special.
俺の鼻は特別製でね
（葉山）中国人？　いや 日本人か
Are you Chinese?
No, you're Japanese.
Huh?
This is no place for a little girl to go sightseeing.
ガキが観光に来る所じゃないぜ
ここは
Hayama Akira
Age 7
I'm 26 years old.
Shiomi Jun
Age 26
私… 26だよ
Huh?!
Candidate Hayama is considered one of the top contenders in these preliminaries!
（由愛）今回の選抜
優勝候補と言われる―
葉山選手 ついに登場です
It's finally his turn to be evaluated!
I believe his dish will be fish head curry.
品目は
フィッシュヘッド･カレーだったね
魚の頭を丸々盛り付ける豪快な…
It's a dynamic dish that uses
the entire fish's head in—
あっ… あれ？
H-Huh?
Wh-What's this?
な… 何だ？
It's much more compact than I'd expected.
えらく小ぶりな…
フィッシュヘッド･カレーじゃない
It's not fish head curry?
（香田）器にふたとして
かぶせられているのは―
I believe what's serving as the "lid" is... naan.
ナンですな
Please crack the naan into the bowl with the spoon as you eat.
スプーンで―
ナンを器に割り入れながら
お召し上がりください
Do take care. It's hot.
熱いのでお気を付けて
It's an explosion... of fragrance!
（創真）香りの…
爆弾！
End
Next Episode
On the next and final episode
of Shokugeki no Souma,
（創真）次回「食戟(しょくげき)のソーマ」
最終回
the twenty-fourth dish:
24品目
Menu
The Banquet
of Warriors
The Banquet of Warriors.
「戦士たちの宴(うたげ)」
Enjoy!
おあがりよ！
That's.. my... spice...
Snore...
Polar Star Dormitory
during Summer Break
Oh, um...
Glad you liked it.